He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall,
and he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
In our time.
many year into break free of the prison of a flat secular materialism to see and to know reality
as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we
permeate everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young post this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation.
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers,
angels of the apocalypse.
You are listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast,
my co-host, Father Stephen D. Young.
The Bane of the Banshee is with me straight from his womb.
That's true to you, and here to the end.
Oh, sorry, nothing, nothing.
Yeah, let me see, and I'm Father of the Stephen D.
In Emeas, Pennsylvania, perched precariously atop
the arcane tower of podcasting, hovering tens.
If not, dozens of...
thousands of stories about a disused gateway to the underworld. We're not live this time.
Or are we? You never know. I mean, how about what happened last week when nobody wants to talk about that.
They're sick of hearing about that big news story last week. I know. Denmark, California,
invasion. I mean, who could have seen that coming? Yeah, Vikings on the loose once again,
But we're not going to be taking any calls this time.
because this is probably a pre-recorded episode. We'll get to those next time, God willing.
So last time we talked about demonic possession, the action of demons generally in the world.
And this time we're flipping the script, talking about the action of angels in the world.
This is very retro 2020 era, Lord of Spirits. So maybe this episode could be a little bit less creepy.
So just will it father? I mean, I'm not saying you have to make promises.
All the angels are wheels with eyes.
Oh, is that creepy?
I mean, a little startling, maybe.
I mean, a little bit, a little weird.
I know it's funny, the quote unquote,
Biblically accurate angels, they never do the wheel bit.
It's always just lots and lots of feathers.
And they try sometimes, there's like,
but it just, it looks like, you know, arm bands
or something like it doesn't really look like a wheel.
Yeah, right, right.
I'm disappointed in all the maimsters.
Come on, you can do better.
like a wheel of the sky that keeps on turning.
Thank you for that. I was having very 80s morning actually. I saw someone did a trailer for Legends of Zelda as if it were like every 80s teen movie.
Which apparently someone made this like like 15 years ago and I came across again. It was very, very amusing.
So look at that. You're just like 15 years behind on the internet is what you're saying.
I did live on Guam for 5
years and that set me 15 years behind. Did you see that chocolate rain video? I have seen that one.
So angels, what's up with angels? Yeah, what's their deal? So yeah, we are going to be talking about
angels and related things.
And yes, like last time,
some of this is gonna be pulling together threads
from previous episodes.
By previous episodes, I mean, very early episodes.
Yeah.
Episodes fraught with all manner of technical difficulties.
So maybe this will help.
But, and so we need to start by, again,
doing a little bit of review, a little bit of,
Some of that.
So that material which we're not going to belabor but we do need to sort of touch on it refresher
Right, so the first thing of course is classically
You know if there's one orthodox thing about angels
That an orthodox person is aware of it's the idea of the ranks of angels
Say Dionysius theory op a guy
Right
those nine ranks being in order
or a serifim.
cherubim thrones dominions, virtues, powers,
principalities, archangels, and angels.
Nice.
Did you read that off from memory?
Probably not.
I can't do sleepy, happy, grumpy, dopey,
Sinesi, bashful, and doc.
Oh nice.
My wife used to have all of the,
towards the night before Christmas memorized, actually,
which I probably do accidentally.
Yeah, I'm not going to try.
I'm not going to change.
We memorized Luke two every year for her.
Yes, that was the.
Yeah.
Now that I said that I'm podcast people are gonna approach my wife and be like okay tell me that you know
They're gonna make her do that. I'm sorry when you get home. Just say you're welcome. Yeah
Should be like what
This is definitely the day to give her such a gift but anyway
Not to let on when we're recording but
Actually she doesn't care about this day
Like she literally actively opposes it
It's a saint's day.
It is a saint's day.
You're saint oxen.
Yes.
Well, everyone knows what if she got to get
St. Oxenius?
I know.
These people who wore against the saints,
I don't get it.
Don't understand.
Deep cut.
Father's divin deep cut.
So yeah, so there's those nine ranks.
Yes.
And so now, but again, we have to,
there are ways of understanding this.
They're less helpful.
So what we have understanding this is that these are sort
species of angel. Yeah, because especially because they're depicted differently. There's a
side of like, oh, it's this kind or it's that kind. Right. And so angels don't have species.
There's a very good reason why they don't have species. They don't reproduce. Right. Right.
That's that's kind of the definition of species is that can reproduce with each other. Right. So
So species kind of doesn't work.
In fact, since they don't reproduce.
And they don't have material bodies technically speaking.
Every angel is sweet generous, right?
It's its own genera, meaning it's unique.
Yeah.
Each angelic being is unique.
So then what are these ranks, right?
It's also not ranks in the sense that like, well, you start out as an angel.
You get your wings, now you're an angel.
And then you kind of work your way up, right?
You put in 15 years.
They make you an archangel.
And then, you know, you keep working hard.
And, you know, maybe you could be a throne someday, kid.
No, it's not.
Right. How it works.
This is these are essentially roles or jobs that they have
that these beings are entrusted with.
That's what puts them...
a particular rank, and then related to that job description, they are nearer or farther
from God. What that means is not literal space obviously, but it refers, it's a reference
to the amount in which they participate in the glory of God. So there is a hierarchy, there
are levels to this, there are levels to which they participated God's grace, allowing them
to perform the job, the tasks.
than are assigned to them by God.
And we talked last time about the fact that,
right, God is doing this out of love,
but we'll talk more about that later today.
But this is obviously,
D&S-EAs, if you understand how the celestial hierarchies
this text works, it works, it functions along with
Alongside
parallel to his ecclesiastical hierarchies. He's making a deliberate comparison.
Right. Yep. Yep. Yep. And a bishop is not a different species than a layperson.
Yeah. A bishop but a layperson are both humans. Right. Right. They just have a different role
at a different task that God has called them to carry out. Right. And just like with the angelic
being the idea is they are to be faithful in carrying
out that role and those tasks.
And there is a hierarchy.
Like it's, you know, summer first, summer second, summer third.
That's just the way that it is.
It doesn't mean that...
My bishop is the boss of me.
Yeah, it doesn't mean your bishop is necessarily a better person than you, now probably.
Yes, in my case, yes.
Yes.
But you know, it's, or holy, or...
It's some of the kids who are better people than me.
I mean, this is...
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So it's not about who's can...
considered to be more holy or anything like that.
You're right.
The other issue related to this that sometimes causes confusion is
so there is this second lowest, quote, unquote lowest,
rank, archangels, right?
And then there are the seven archangels.
And sometimes people get confused about this.
So they assume that those seven arc angles.
We're not going to talk about them a lot tonight.
We've talked about past episodes we have.
St. Michael and Gabriel, Raphael, Yuri,
and then others depending on which one you're looking at,
from which father.
But those seven are in this second lowest rank.
Some folks assume, or some folks assume that that second lowest rank
lowest rank only have
seven members, even though, for example, the liturgy at one point in one of the prayers,
we talk about there being thousands of archangels and 10,000s of angels.
Yeah. They're like, well, wait a minute. I thought there were seven archangels, right?
So we have to remember how arc or arch works as a title. It just means first, literally, or chief.
right, ranking. So like
there are archbishop and arch priests, right? And so that could be used to indicate this rank
of which there are thousands of members, but it can also be used as it is with the seven
to say, these are the seven chief angels out of all the angels of all the ranks.
Right? And if you pick close attention to the church's tradition, this is born out, for example,
the cynics are the feasts of Saint Michael say that
he's a seraphim. There's the reference, of course, in Revelation to the seven
spirits who stand before the throne of God, which is part of how they
Raphael introduces himself in Tobit that we talked about. Yes, exactly.
Yeah, so the seven archangels don't necessarily belong to the rank archangels,
And the rank of archaegals includes a lot more than just those.
than just seven. So that term, arc angels, be used in different ways. So we understand
and it's pretty clear when we read the Old Testament, right? We see lots of angels doing
things right and we kind of see this
sort of authority structure. God sends angels to do things. Angels are sort of intermediaries
for various things. Second temple tradition for example, there's sort of an angelic intermediary,
or angelic intermediaries in terms of the giving of the Torah and Mount Sinai, etc. Angels get sent
with messages, archives will get set with messages, St. Rafael and Tobit. We're not going to rehearse every-
example of angels of the Old Testament now, but that God sort of administers things and
sends his messengers, and ministers the creation through these angelic beings.
Often however, when we get to the New Testament, we have this particular mode of thinking that
It comes from a particular Protestant tradition that we've all kind of inherited in the
...
United States where we act as if all of that kind of drops out. Right? Because now we don't get a lot of talk about in our common in the common sort of Christian world parlance in the United States I'm talking about now.
Everyone, you don't hear anyone saying, you know, I prayed to be here.
and God sent an angel to heal me.
Yeah.
Right.
Like that's just not a way of speaking.
But used to be.
Covetly used to be, but it's not.
Right.
Yeah.
Everything is sort of.
God directly.
Yeah, this is right.
Flattened.
Higher.
That just has God above.
And then everybody else.
Yeah.
And so as if.
Right.
You know, well, yes.
Yes, these angels had all these jobs.
had all these tasks, did all these things before Christ.
There's a big reduction in force.
Yes, there were just massive layoffs
to the heavenly deep state like
at Christ's decision, right?
And now I guess they're just out of work.
But of course there's no reason to believe that, right?
Rather, rather what we see happen
in Christ's incarnation and ascension and look at the hymns of the feast of the ascension
and now what they say in terms of angels.
What has changed is that through the incarnation through Christ becoming man and then through
him taking our humanity and elevating it to the throne of God, humanity has sort of ascended
that hierarchy.
ascended that authority structure. He brews gets into this a lot. So that now there's
depending on whether you want to count the nine ranks down with Seraphim being rank one
or you want to count the other way with angels being rank one, there's either a new rank
one or ten. Or rank zero. Or rank zero, zero through nine if you want to go that way.
it is.
glorified humanity. Yeah, right, say, sing glory. And also for this, see him's to the
Theotokos, right? More honorable than the cherubim, more glorious than the saraphim.
Yeah, which those are the highest ranks of angels. So if she's above that, that's a higher rank.
Right. And a word here about the Theotokos.
That's because
I know we have non-orthodox listeners and non-Roman Catholic listeners who probably involuntarily,
even if they don't want to, get a little bit of heebie-gb's when we start talking about
the Theotokos, okay?
But on this point and on all these points, right, you have to remember that for the Orthodox
church, the Theotokos is the greatest human saint.
Right.
And so when we're talking about human saints, we're talking about redeemed humanity, glorified humanity.
We use her as the primary example because she is the prime example of a glorified human
of a human who has dedicated their life to God. Now some of you may be thinking, why don't we use
Jesus because Jesus is God.
Yeah, he didn't have to repent.
And I'm not.
But I am a human like the Theotokos.
But the things we say about the Theotokos of this regard are true of glorified humanity in general, in many cases.
She's just being used as an exemplar.
Yeah, the difference between her and other saints is really a difference of degree.
Right. Quantitative, not quality.
Yeah, and in this particular case obviously there's certain unique things about her
She gives birth to God himself which no one else does
Right, but there are other things we say about her that give people the he be jeepies like that
She can actually commit sins that we also say about like Saint John the forerunner. Yeah
Yeah, we say about Saint John the forerunner people might give you a weird look
But they don't get the he be jeepies the same way and so if you're one of those folks you should think about that for a minute
And what is it that's really giving you the hemigemies of the hypothaotocos?
Is it just you've had some kind of romophobia hammered into you from childhood, right?
I say this is a Dutch person.
Like that happens to people sometimes.
So yeah.
So she's the example of, but she is an example of, right?
has been glorified in Christ, right?
and therefore has a sentence in Jealousy hierarchy.
And what we mean by that again is not that now she's like
part of the Trinity or goddess, right, or something like this.
In those kind of sentences, what we mean by that is, again,
redeemed humanity, glorified humanity is like another rank,
meaning has tasks, right,
has things that they do.
on behalf of God, right? Things that God has them do, right?
And this is something that I think everybody of any
even vaguely Christian stripe agrees on in terms of the world to come.
But we're talking about the life of the world to come.
We're talking about the resurrection. We're talking about eternal life.
Oh yeah.
We're gonna have all these jobs, we're gonna have things where I'm just gonna be sitting around to anything unless you're a stare at the orb type
Yeah, it's explicit in the scriptures, you know, right so yeah, the age to come is subject, you know
It's not two angels that the age to come is subject, you know, right St. Paul says right
but it seems like
For a large segment of folks, especially American evangelicals
They think the glorified saints just sort of twiddle their thumbs until then
Right, like they're not doing anything.
They reject soul sleep.
They're asleep.
They're conscious.
They're in heaven or with Christ or however it wants to be raised.
But they're not doing anything.
Playing harps.
Yeah.
Well, in clouds.
And see, you can see how this is part and parcel the same problem we mentioned earlier.
Because the angels are so also aren't really doing anything in the New Testament.
Hey!
Yeah, yeah, for a lot of those folks. Yeah, right. There's just sort of these
There's a joying life I guess or enjoy PE Gagels. I don't know
Singing I don't know
all the time but right that but
This sense of having a role in a task
Sort of gets bracketed off for this new testament era and some kind of weird celestial
Dispensationalism right then oh yeah in the old testament
Yes, and in the world to come.
but not now. Right now it's just God doing everything directly. Right. But this idea, this
understanding, right, when you take the understanding of angels and the roles, right, that's clearly in
the Old Testament scriptures, when you take the idea we've talked about before on the show,
about replacing fallen angelic beings,
about glorified humans replacing fallen angelic beings.
And then you add in the New Testament teaching
of the incarnation of Christ,
that transcends even replacing angels,
to, you know, man was made a little lower than the angels,
but exalted with glory and honor,
first of all in Christ,
and then Christ gives that benefit.
to us, right?
It's something that that's where the whole concept of saints comes from.
Yeah.
In the church.
Yeah, it's not so weird.
Add on, you know.
Yeah.
It's part parcel of.
Yes, they assume the kind of duties and do the kind of things that we see angels doing
in the Old Testament.
Yeah, I mean, you just kind of listed off like delivering messages, protecting people,
Pairing prayers passing
them on to God. Yeah, and especially if you include all of church history, you see them
doing things, you know, like being present at like alterations of the landscape, you know,
stuff like this, right? There's, you know, all the kind of stuff that you see angels doing
in the Old Testament, human saints are doing in the under the New Covenant. Right. Yeah.
Right, and that will then continue.
in the life of the world to come.
Right, I mean, this is why Jesus describes,
sons of the resurrection is equal to the angels in Luke 20,
36.
Right, and the idea of venerating them,
meaning showing them honor,
is just the opposite of the biblical warnings
we get in the New Testament against slandering angels.
Ever what are those about?
We were just
accidentally slandered Angel, I don't get that a lot in confession.
Now, I was talking trash.
I'm like, already an angel.
Oh, man.
Don't do that.
Your guardian angel might be my switch sides on you.
You know, that's a big no.
Yeah.
So no for me, dog.
So what that also means is that we talked last time about
So we reviewed sort of
last time about what a spirit is, right? Is that as being sort of a level of consciousness
above human consciousness that can sort of animate and motivate human consciousnesses,
right, on a collective level? Well, that means when someone becomes a saint, they become
a spirit in that sense.
See your spirit episodes.
Yeah, they exist in the noetic world in the world of thoughts, the world of the mind and and
they are able to then both angels and
glorified humans are able to then
function in that way right and what is that way? What is what is the goal? Well, it's the opposite of what the demons do
Right, it's influencing and directing and guiding and shepherding.
but towards God rather than towards destruction.
Right. And so the demons have an end in themselves just destroying people.
They have no greater purpose. They're not trying to get you to go worship Satan.
They don't care. They'll destroy you however they can.
They could do that through casual boring depressive atheism.
right, and if that's the way to destroy you, that's...
how they'll do it. Yeah, whatever it takes. They don't care. Right. But angels have this
very specific and the saints have this very specific purpose of guiding people toward
God. Right. And St. Dionysius and others say this was the purpose of the angels who God put
over the nations was to guide them back to God. Right. After God had to distance himself
from them because of their sin at Bable.
So this idea of guiding and shepherding,
right, is what they do.
And again, this is what's going on with the Theratokas and why she's
an example.
She always directs the leads people to her son.
Yeah.
In fact, in many icons, she's literally pointing at him.
Yes.
Yeah.
And she's always depicted with him.
Not always always.
Well, it's up.
She's supposed to be always depicted.
I mean, there is a true.
That is a rule, but like every other rule
of the Orthodox Church, that is.
But there is a tradition of icons of her
at the moment of the enunciation, in particular.
Well, but even there, there's the beam, right?
Where she's in the picture.
Yeah, but, but yes, overall, that's true.
I just had to get in my chance to, I'm actually you, you know.
Yo, yo, you better shot. See if you're gonna have actually...
You should have brought up the icons of her birth.
Oh, there's that too.
Or it's just like her as the the abyss of Mount Athos.
Yeah, that's kind of thing, right?
You know, protection, holy protection.
Like every rule of the Orthodox Church,
there's exceptions, right?
Yes.
But when you're just depicting her, right?
So you can have a depiction of St John the Forerunner
or St Nicholas, just an icon of them.
that doesn't have Jesus in it.
Yeah, but you don't have it. I could have the you're not supposed to have it. I could have the theotokos like that without Jesus
And of course as soon as you refer one of the reasons why we refer to her all the time as the theotokos is that keeps Christ in the picture
Yeah, birth giver to God. Yeah
But so that's that's again
Christ, but St. John the Forerunner, right? A lot of icons, especially icons that are
going next to an icon of Christ, or where Christ is in the icon, he's bowing toward him,
right? Gesturing toward him, pointing at him, right? And this is the case of all of the
saints, right? They're pointing you, leading you, directing you to Christ.
So one could ask the question.
Why doesn't God just come to humanity directly? Why all the why the administrative state? Yeah, wouldn't that be more efficient?
You know, there's a God need to cut the waste
That whole you know bureaucratic layoffs again at the ascension. Yeah
Yeah.
So there's a couple things we have to say about that.
Number one.
Sometimes God does.
Yeah.
So see Abraham Isaac and Jacob.
Yes, he does talk directly to people sometimes.
He appears directly, he shows the eats with them, right?
He wrestles them.
Yeah.
I'm more Adam and Eve, I mean, for crying out loud, right?
Yeah, I mean, very directly.
So God does that sometimes.
And of course, see Christ in the New Testament, right?
But he doesn't always do that.
Um,
And there's something important to say, as we've said, as we just alluded to with the
Tower of Babel and with the flood.
The presence of God, the direct presence of God is highly dangerous to sinful humanity.
And so there's that, that sort of approach can end up causing a flood and wiping out humanity.
no one wants that.
No, what was that but there's something more important than that right because it's clear from him appearing to Abraham and Isaac and especially Jacob who are not exactly
Sinless that God can do that without killing someone if he wants to sure sure right
So it's not that it's it's beyond God but the more important thing that we alluded to a little bit ago is that
Is the whole reason why God created created anything?
And that's love.
love. Yeah, which is not exactly efficient. Why is there anything rather than nothing? Right?
Because of God's love. That's what we created beings like us and like angels and other critters,
right, to share his love and his life with out of his love. And so a big part of love is sharing.
We've now turned into Mr. Rogers.
But, uh...
Yeah, and I've said it before and I'll say it again. Fred Rogers is the one saint produced
by Presbyterianism. Huh? They got one. Okay. Only one. But they got one. I do hope that
they will dedicate a church to him or something or at least some kind of building. Yeah,
I mean, they ought to have something dedicated. Yeah. Yeah. Up Pittsburgh, Shrine. You know,
A lot of this particular critique is...
is based on this idea of efficiency.
Like God can't just directly go, you know, whatever.
Why through saints, why through angels.
But like efficiency,
while a significant component of day-to-day human life
and, you know, communal life and government,
whatever, whatever, whatever,
is completely irrelevant to an omnipotent being.
Like in what sense does efficiency matter
when there's no limits, right?
And just think about it for a second, boys and girls.
It doesn't matter if you're God.
It doesn't matter.
Have you seen the sound of music?
I have seen the sound of music.
Right.
Are you gonna try and run your family
with ruthless efficiency?
Have we learned nothing from rockers at Hammerstein?
Ha, ha, ha.
Oh.
You gotta open up to love.
If you want to escape the Nazis. But anyway, yes. But yeah, right? And so yes, God doesn't
need angels. He doesn't need us. He doesn't need me. No, he can't do anything he like.
He doesn't need me to celebrate liturgy in order to work in the lives of my parishioners.
No, no. He doesn't. He can work directly in their lives if he wants to. Yeah. Right? But he's
given me that privilege.
out of love, right? And him giving me that privilege out of love, that way of him using
that way of working in the lives through the Eucharist, through the sacraments of my
parishioners also has created this community of parishioners. That's a community of love.
who love each other and God help them even love me for some reason, right?
That's all created by the way that God does this.
That's what we're talking about when we say that God is doing this out of love, right?
And for the purpose of love.
And so yes, he doesn't need to send the archangel Gabriel to the Theotokos.
Yeah.
He could have just told the Theotokos directly.
But he gives this
this mission to the archangel Gabriel, who read our
hemnography, right? Read the biblical text. This archangel,
this highest ranking angelic being is like honored and
awed by this task he's been given. Right? That's a gift.
the God gave him. Right. And so, I mean that's really what I'm...
by, you know, try running your family, try operating,
functioning in your marriage based on efficiency. Right.
Look, I told you last month that I love you. Yeah.
As unchanged, no time for this discussion. I mean, I have
worked to do. Right? Like you, that dog don't hunt, right?
Or try racing your kids based on ruthless efficiency.
Watch what happens.
I can tell you I can word you in advance they'll all go crazy the second they get out from under your thumb
So yeah, and so that's not how God operates right
That's not how God operates
That's not really how we want him to operate
Yeah, do you want you're a relationship to God to be barked by ruthless efficiency?
Okay.
Right.
I'm ready, guys.
Yeah, you are not necessary to the equation. So maybe not, right?
Yeah, now again, I
Want to make very clear. We're not saying that there's something God can't do
Yeah, I mean you can also use fear and surprise in addition to ruthless efficiency. Yes, and a
Financial devotion to the Pope
The which I do not have by the way
Yeah.
I was gonna ask, fanatical or even non-fanatical.
All right, but yeah, we're not saying
that there's something God can't do.
As we said before on the show,
anytime you see any theological principle
or theological point being made,
that's premised on there being something God can't do.
Right?
You know you should reject it.
You know this is nonsense.
saying God can't do blank, right?
Even if they say something to you like God can't sin.
Yeah, that's the time to interrogate what they mean by sin.
Mean by yeah, exactly.
What's going on there, right?
Something that seems like, well, okay, that sounds right.
Well,
Uh, um, nonetheless.
God can do anything He wants.
Nonetheless, what we see, what's revealed to us in the world,
what we know of God is His working in the world,
His operations, His activities.
And we observe that God works in certain ways,
based on love, based on sharing, based on...
These are ways that we observe him working.
right? And that's how we know who he is. And so we don't base, right, our discourse on
God on what we think he can and can't do. We base our discourse on God on how we see
him working and what we see him doing. And what we see him doing in the scriptures, right?
through the description.
is operating through agents, working through means in the world.
The way he usually expresses his love for people is not like directly beaming it into their
soul or their heart.
Honestly, it isn't.
It's through other people.
That's the most common way God shows his love.
And this is all of these things.
All of these things. This is why the book of Acts is so important. The book of Acts gets treated
like it's just sort of an epilogue to the Gospels, right? And St. Luke's Gospel in particular.
But the book of Acts is very important for a bunch of reasons, but some of those reasons are what
we're getting at right here. So for example, we see angels coming and doing things
in the book of acts just like they did in the old
That seems to imply that there's not a change in the role of angels after Christ's ascension.
Yeah.
If they're still doing the same things, like letting, letting's say Peter at a prison.
Right.
So there's not, we see there's not a big shift there.
Also importantly, if someone were motivated to make the point that like,
Well, okay, no, now there's Jesus, right?
So we have these old Testament figures.
Yeah, those old figures,
Testament figures were important
because they're sort of types of Christ.
They sort of point us to who Jesus will be.
But now we have Jesus.
So like none of that's important anymore.
We just focus on Jesus
except the book of Acts is in the New Testament.
And is mostly about St. Paul.
Yeah, I mean,
he also St. Philip, St. Stephen, St. Peter.
Here's the fun bit at the very beginning.
St. Luke writes in the previous, in my former treatise, O theophilus. I love that translation.
But referring to his gospel, he says, it's our last episode. Yeah, exactly. Volume one,
this is, you know, acts as volume two. You know, I wrote about all the things that Jesus began to do
into preach, meaning that the book of Acts, which is basically, frankly, the earliest collection of
saints lives, Christians saints.
lives, but mostly St. Paul, is Jesus continuing to do and to preach.
Right.
But he's doing that through human agents.
There was disciples and apostles.
There's apostles being the ones he sent out to do these things.
Yeah.
They assigned these tasks.
So even in the New Testament, right, God is administering His creation, working in His
creation through means which includes glorified human say
It includes the angels as it always has, and it includes humans here on Earth.
Yep. Yep. So, all right, well that's our first half for this episode we're talking about angels, and we'll be right back.
The centuries after the Protestant Reformation brought about a radical reinterpretation of the epistles of St. Paul,
disconnected from any historical reality.
The Paul operated during his entire life as a f-
faithful Pharisee within the Roman Jewish world.
In St. Paul the Pharisee, Jewish Apostle to all nations
Father Stephen D. Young surveys Paul's life in writings,
interpreting them within the holy tradition
of the Orthodox Church.
This survey is followed by D. Young's interpretive translation
of St. Paul's epistles, which deliberately avoids
overly familiar terminology.
By using words and ideas grounded in first century Judaism,
The young hopes to unsettle commonly held no-
and help the reader reassess Saint Paul
in his historical context.
Available now at store.angianfaith.com
again, that is store.angianfaith.com.
Alright, we're back. It's the second half of this pre-recorded episode of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
If you call, we will not answer.
Someone else?
Someone might though, so see what happens.
Probably not. Don't bug Trudy.
We gave her the night off.
Well, then she won't answer the phone.
I thought we'll see.
We'll be the exactly.
Someone else could be working late.
I'd be like, oh, I wonder who's calling.
That's what I'm saying.
Maybe they'd like some telephonic company.
Could be.
They're burned in the midnight oil.
Yeah, we're talking about angels.
Last time we talked about demons in their activity
in the world.
And this time, we're talking about angels
and their activity in the world.
And we just did a kind of review, actually,
of a lot of stuff that we've discussed
in previous episodes.
Who are angels?
What are angels?
What do they do in the scriptures?
And then also...
the fact that God works through agents, you know,
that are not always directly.
And that's okay,
because he doesn't need to be efficient,
because he's God, and he loves us and wants to share.
How about that?
Just go watch the town of music, seriously.
I know, I kind of wonder sometimes, like,
what people's view of God is,
that they think that efficiency is this really important thing.
Like, how do they understand who God is?
Is he God?
I mean, is it...
definitely a capitalist. I mean, we know that for sure.
He's definitely blessed as a preacher. It's by giving them a lot of money.
Yeah, clearly. Yeah.
And you know, like he's sitting on top of some big machine, you know,
that works in a particular way that he set up.
You know, I feel like that's, that's the notion of God that says that he has to be
efficient. That saints and angels are not really, you know,
Do you have to go through them?
You know, we'll talk more about that, of course, as we go.
So, all right.
So let's talk a little bit more about angels as they actually, as we
experience them, as they're actually acting in the world,
in a more experiential level, and not just a sort of theoretical level, but we've
been talking about.
Yeah.
So yeah, as we said, angels have jobs, right?
They have assignments.
Yeah.
They have roles that they play is actually the better term.
And because job, we don't want to get too literal, again, God not a capitalist per se.
We don't want to get too literal about the job's thing.
There's no promotions as we talked about, right?
But the tasks and assignments of angels can change, right?
If you, right, so Dark Angel Gabriel, when he appears in Scripture.
is doing different things. So like what he's doing in Daniel for example and what he's
doing when he comes to the Theotokos are two different missions, tasks, roles, jobs, right?
So there are different things, right? And of course those could be taken away because
as we talked about under the heading of demons,
there are angels who...
fell, there are other reasons why God takes these away, the angels who were placed over
the nations didn't fulfill their task. And as we've talked about before, the show,
C Saul 82, right, which is the judgment they received for that. And then C Matthew, the
end of Matthew 28, and Christ saying, right before his ascension, all authority in heaven
that on Earth has been.
given to me, therefore go make disciples of all nations.
Yeah, I mean, could it be said that when they walked off the job that they that they
ghosted?
No.
Okay.
Because they didn't actually walk off the job.
Oh, they had to they had to be escorted out by security.
Oh, that's yes, true.
So.
Okay.
I thought I had to be some little joke there, but no.
Yeah, you're trying.
I'm more or not.
I'm getting some new material.
I got to try.
You're still working.
working it out on the road. Yeah, that's right. But yeah, if
for anyone who still doubts that interpretation we just
quickly gave, I would note to you that in the Holy Saturday
Liturgy, we sing Psalm 82, and then we read the end of Matthew
28. So, yeah, directly, it's all maybe you is sung as the
gospel hymn. Yes, exactly. That gospel read exactly. It's
not it replaces the ala luya so like it's
it's literally connected to the gospel. It's not just a thing that comes before it.
Yes, right.
Directly connected.
Yeah.
Yeah, seeing somebody introduces that gospel reading. So the church has ruled on this liturgy
clay, folks.
Yeah.
You know, so take your your parcel of half fake, patristic quotes you've got from chat GPT
and you'll found sand. Thank you.
Sadly, a real thing.
I don't know.
But yeah, so probably the the assignment when we're thinking about different roles and tasks
that angels are assigned, probably the one that's most, as Father Andrew said at the beginning of
this half, that's most experientially relevant to us is our guardian angel, right? The one that's
assigned to me, right? Because I'm a narcissist, that's the most important.
one. So, and so again this is something we get questions about because we've talked about this
on the show. And I know this is a fiction. I know folks can't help it, right? And they're trying to
get over it. But we still have this spreadsheet thing where we're trying to fill in our boxes. And so
So one of the questions we get it off a lot is, right?
Because of course there's...
tradition and it's in the prayers that a guardian angel is assigned to someone when they're baptized.
And this overtime has gotten us a legion of questions about well what if I was Chris made it?
Right. Does that mean anybody who's not in the other extra, it doesn't have a guardian angel?
Does the baby not have a guardian angel until it gets baptized? Does you know
So what about, you know,
later on in the liturgy, in the litneys, where we ask for an angel of peace, a faithful
guide, a guardian for our souls and bodies. Why do we have to ask for one if we got what
assigned one at baptism? When we say the prayers for someone who's traveling, why do we ask
God to send an angel like St. Raphael with Tobit, if you already have one? Right? And people
Get very good.
confused. That's because you're trying to put these things in boxes, right? They don't have
to be in boxes. Let them breathe. Right? Poetry is okay. It does it all have to be pros.
Amen.
And so yes, it is true. Although on hand, that there is a tradition we believe that a person
is baptized because of the Christian they have an angel.
to watch over them and spiritually protect them.
And most importantly, do what we were talking about in the last half,
guide them in their life toward God, toward Christ.
That is the guardian angel's most important task to help guide.
But we also pray all the time for that angel to watch over us and protect us.
Right. Yeah. And because as we just said,
can change. Some of those prayers have as their subtext. Man, I've been doing a lot of rotten stuff
that my guardian angel being holy doesn't want to know about it doesn't want to see.
Don't take them away. Yeah. And then there's also, you know, I still need his help.
right that 1983 scorpion song send me a needle right now.
Yeah.
Um, that was for our European listeners.
Um, so yeah, so we don't have to totally nail this down, right?
But yes.
Oh, man, that Amy Grant, so I'm just came into my head.
Oh, night bare fuel.
Okay, moving on.
Do you need to take a moment, father?
I need, why do you stiff drink?
But I don't think I should take one on the air.
Um.
So.
But so angels, right?
Also.
Uh, it's important.
Recognize.
Just like demons angels have their own agency.
Right.
Uh, angels are not just like.
Sock puppets God uses.
Right.
Yeah.
or inanimate tools, right? They have a will. But the reason it's important to make this point
is our weird distorted view of free will. Right? Our weird, this is a very modern thing.
Distorted version of free will is, well, demons have free will because demons do what they want,
but angels don't because angels just do whatever God tells them. Right?
We'll first.
If they don't have free will, how did they end up being demons?
That's...
Yeah.
Right.
But checkmate.
Yeah.
Take that.
But no, angels have their own agency.
The fact that you voluntarily align your will and your activity with God's will and God's
activity, like we were talking about in the last episode, the fact that you choose to
do that does not mean you don't have free will.
right because you have freely done that. Right. I mean, this is one of the things that sometimes people
yeah skeptics have religion quote unquote will sometimes say like you well you only think that
are do that because you're you're priest to your pastor your bishop told you to you know I'm like
that one's making me be here. Yeah. You know. I am on my own reconnaissance. Yeah. Yeah.
That's an even and this is this is important principle
and orthodox life, right? And we've talked about this on the show before, we're talking about
like the concept of obedience, right? For obedience to be obedience, it has to be freely given.
Yeah, it's a voluntary aligning. I mean literally voluntary. That means according to the will.
If you're enslaved, right? You are not being obedient. You are being threatened and punished and
force to do things, right? Like, that's not the same thing.
As someone in authority telling you to do something and you voluntarily obeying that command
Right, those are two different things
So yeah, and that's so angels are the same way right they have their own agency as
Spirits their spirits about ideas. They're not sock puppets, right. They're not drones
bones right there.
The other eight is and they, right, as we just alluded to.
How did they get to be demons?
Okay.
Little more detail because we talk about this.
We've talked about, you know, we've talked about all the time, angels falling.
And we've talked about that with a little more nuance, I think, on this show than a lot of
places.
But what does that concretely mean and how concretely does that happen?
Right?
even used some
terminology where if you press it like, what does that mean? So like what we've talked about
the angels who are set over the nations, we've talked about the, you know, the, the, the humans
of that nation start worshipping them as gods and we've used language like, well, they accept it.
Yeah, what does that mean? What does that mean?
What does that mean?
Behind some altar somewhere and and just give me give me give me that that that means. Yeah.
Yes, thank you for the smoke. Thank you for putting those bones, right?
Is it like in the Iliad, you know?
whether or not they're going, smells great.
I'm going to give you favor and war.
Yeah.
That's right.
So what that means is what we're talking about is we're
talking about an angelic being aligning its will
with a human will.
So this is why in each of the angelic falls, I'll
of them, we reiterated last time, there is this human component, right? It is
commensurate with some group of humans also falling. Right. It's not this
separate event that we sort of hear about objectively. Right. And so in each
of those cases, every time that happens, there is some angelic being and some
human being or being.
right? Who align their wills with each other over against aligning themselves with God's will.
Right. So,
and Gellik Falls happened in communion with humanity.
Yeah, which is, I mean, this is why St. Paul says, don't eat pagan sacrifices,
because that's basically don't.
to communion with demons.
Because they're gonna drag you down.
Right.
And this is, I mean, they understood this.
St. Paul understands this,
the passage of first Corinthians,
you're talking about reflects that,
but this is how the pagans understood it.
They were in communion with their gods.
They were part of a community with their gods.
Right, and there was this relate.
Right?
Of give and take, right, and of being shaped, right?
And you can see Plato talking about the age of Kronus where the gods were first
Assigned and they were all sort of peaceful and merciful shepherds. And then something happened.
And now not so much for Plato, right?
Yeah, and so that's that sort of concrete living.
If you want the how that happens, that's how that happens. And by the way, that is the answer to the whole puzzling question people roll over it over again, all the time of like, well, wait, how can angels be mutable.
If they don't have physical bodies, why can't they repent, right? Maybe you, right? Because this happens, right? In terms of humans who do have physical bodies that are mutable.
Hmm.
That has happened.
to communion with humans. And you know those minority report of weird stories where you
do see a demon, something happens akin to repentance, that become an angel again, there's a few
stories that desert fathers where that happens. In every one of those stories, it's through
communion with a human, particularly holy human.
Yeah, which kind of suggests a human saint. Humans have power over angels.
Yes.
That...
through whom they're almost like we're going to judge them someday. Huh, I feel like I read that
somewhere. Yeah. Like we're in the hierarchy above them. Glorified humans are in the hierarchy
above them. It's almost like that. Yeah. A lot of what St. Paul says in this regard assumes the
incarnation. Right. Even though he never straight comes out and says, and this is why again,
Somebody like Bart Irman even thinks he now roughly thinks that St. Paul was an Aryan.
He doesn't think he isn't fully very yet, but he has moved from the position that St. Paul didn't think Jesus was divine to.
Oh no, there is some kind of incarnation thing happening here in the background that's fundamental to his logic.
Come on over Bart Irman right at the show.
So almost there.
Yeah, you're going.
Keep going.
Next live show, Colin, and we'll talk about it.
Yeah, absolutely.
We'll just clear everything off the thing.
Well, I will.
I will clear the next and just talk to Bart Irman for three hours.
If you can talk for three hours.
I doubt he wants to talk to me for three hours.
I don't know that he wants to talk to me for five minutes,
but I really doubt three hours.
But open invitation.
But I would if he wanted to.
And yeah.
So.
But so what that showing is, again, we talked about this last time, humans have a
news, have a mind, right? We are the type of being that overlaps the spiritual
world, the world of thoughts, the noetic world, and the physical material world.
Right? And we experience all of that together. Again, that's kind of the theme of
this show.
Alright.
The overarching theme of the show is that he was experienced all of that, even if they
wanted to nigh part of it.
They still experience it and participate in it.
And jealous beings are in that noetic layer of the created world.
My dogs are in the physical material part of that creation.
being's overlap it.
And so that's why there is, in the same way, that humanity has a certain relationship
to the rest of the material creation.
Vizavi representing it to God, right?
Humanity also has a role, especially a light of the incarnation, in terms of the duetic realm,
of intervals and demons.
And that's what St. Paul is getting at there with the judging angels.
But so that world, that world of thoughts, that noetic world, that world of the news,
that we perceive through our mind, that's where angels, not just demons, but also angels
operate primarily when you're not seeing them, which is most of the time.
In that world of thoughts, just as demons come.
and throw thoughts at us. Sometimes describe his darts, that whole Rechef analogy that comes
through the Psalms. Angels come with positive thoughts, with godly thoughts, right?
Thoughts of God. And those likewise are thoughts that we can choose to focus on.
Let's see.
Pause.
whatever is good, whatever is pure, whatever is noble, think on these things.
Yeah, I mean, we all have this experience too, right? Like you'd be just doing something and then
something very good will occur to you. And if you're like me, you kind of go, that's nice and move
on most of the time. But I'll back to this social media post that's making me angry. Yeah, exactly.
But you know, just to, hey, pay attention to those thoughts a little bit more if you can.
You know, and think, wait, could I do that?
Usually the answer is yes.
Right. And the, the, and as we talked about last time, those are the thoughts
that we need to be building into ideas.
Yeah, like work with that.
And ideas that we then act upon, right?
And then we then put to work in our lives, put into our life.
Yeah. Right.
Yeah.
Rather than the other thoughts.
Right.
Yeah.
This is part of what we're talking about last time with replacing the negative with the pot.
Right.
The idea is these things, these good things.
we take those focus on.
those and build those. Yeah, I mean, a thought comes into your head. It's good to ask this
question of the thought. Is this thought going to help my salvation or harm it? And, you know,
usually the answer to that question is pretty straightforward and easy. And then, you know,
based on that, you can focus on the thought or tell it to take a hike. Yeah, yeah. Now,
Now we have to make a note here.
because there's another place where
the sort of Calvinist, Puritan, Protestant tradition
rears its ugly head
in American evangelicalism.
And that's that, this stuff we're talking about
with angels and thoughts.
If you're used to hearing anything like that
in the American Christian world,
It's probably all a trimming-
into the Holy Spirit.
Yeah, the Holy Spirit told me.
Yeah, the Holy Spirit told me this.
Often it's, the Holy Spirit told me to tell you.
Yeah, you know.
The Holy Spirit gave me this or, you know.
Yeah.
God.
The thing that always ground my gears when I hear somebody,
I was going to talk about something totally different,
but the Holy Spirit really laid it on my heart
to say this.
Yes.
Say something that's just absolutely incorrect
about the Bible.
Yeah.
verifiably factually incorrect. And I'm like, that wasn't the Holy Spirit, bro.
I yeah, God laid it on my heart. That's the thing you hear a lot.
Technically, you just blasphemed.
No, that is. That's blasphemy. Yeah. No, I know your own words and claiming
they're the words of God. Yeah. Okay.
But maybe God told you something that isn't true. That's blasphemy.
I think, yeah, I think it's because that's, you know, people,
for whatever reason, people have been trained that a strong feeling or a good
feeling.
or something making sense to them equals the action of God directly on them.
Right. And you can weaponize this. Yeah. And people give me a recent example
that I found fascinating. So prominent Protestant internet apologist.
Okay.
My personal favorite Roman Catholic apologist, I'm not going to name any names here, but my personal
favorite Roman Catholic apologists for various reasons.
Uh, makes a video just like logically point by point annihilating this whole talk given
by this Protestant, right, apologist.
Okay.
So of course, people, both people on the Roman Catholic side and people on the Protestant
Apoges side.
Want the Protestant apologists to respond to this
Okay, so
Deluge of things hey, or you're gonna respond to this or you can respond to this man
Like it really sounds like you kind of wreck your battleship, right? Like you're totally poned
Yeah, like are you when you get respond to this are you ready for the response they got
For all sides got I'm concerned so will he address this sitting on the edge of my seat here?
Do you want
person's name
to spend time on this rather than the things God has given him to talk about.
Wow!
Amazing.
So, yeah, talk about weaponization, right?
I know.
And what is buried in there?
claim that every video this guy released
is on YouTube is coming from God. Right. Right? Yeah. This isn't a charismatic guy who would call
himself a prophet, but he's basically claiming to be a prophet when he says, I know. It's
and it's, you know, it's, it's, it's, it's just, it's obviously wrong on its face. Right? Because,
because the problem is the people who make these claims for themselves or about the guy that they're
are sipping for.
What about the fact that other people who are making those exact same
say things that contradict what you know profit number one is saying then you have to pick between them and then it's like
Well, why should you pick this guy and not this guy? You know, why is this sort of opinions the this is these sort of opinions from the Holy Spirit
There's one guy has it which I mean, okay. Yes. That's theoretically possible, but that's not Christianity, you know
right. This is not the Messiah, right? I actually read someone someone the other day on on the tweeters say
you know, if you dislike so-and-so, speaking of an Orthodox figure online, if you
just like so-and-so, then you oppose the church fathers. Whatever. I'm like, ah,
your buddy there is not Jesus, you know. Yeah, you know. He is not like church
fathers even. Yeah, he's also not, yeah, exactly. Like, you know. He's not even one of
the church rather. I'm like oops yeah you kind of.
did an idolatry there. Yeah he's not even a saint yet right exactly maybe
someday exactly yeah it ain't easy oh stops everyone like if you are an adult
man okay there are ways you should never talk to another adult man
But I get emails anyway, just stop right.
email. But so here's what we're saying. We're not just, hey, let's pick on the way
evangelicals talk. That's not that's honestly not what we're trying to do right now.
No, no, no.
What we're trying to say is, and the reason I gave the example I gave is that's where that
just a way of taught. Well, yeah, that's just a way of talking. You got kind of weaponized
it a weird way, right? Yeah. Like to shut down discussion to not half
to be accountable. Have some restraint. Like it's like say, no, just here you say this,
you say this because this is what we're saying the truth is, right? You say a thought occurred to me.
Right? And I think it's a good one. And here's my idea based on that.
Yeah. Here's my fallible idea, right? Because as we talked about, when you move last time,
when you move from a thought to an idea, your subjectivity comes into it. My subjectivity comes
is it?
Yeah, you're engaged.
Therefore, it's fallible.
That's right.
Yeah.
And that thought did come from God through an angel.
I might get it wrong.
Right.
I think there should just be a whole lot more, a whole lot less of God laid it on my heart
and a whole lot more.
It seems to me.
Yeah.
This is coming from me.
Like, this is coming from me, not directly from God, not even directly from an angel.
It's coming from me.
Right?
Yep.
But I think...
this is right that's you know yeah that you don't get as many clicks that way
fathers none of my books yeah I had a really disappointed parishioner because I
pointed out to them that if I went back and read religion of the Apostles right
now right that I wrote I technically I wrote it like six years ago yeah right that I
would probably think that some of it is not correct.
Right? Because I've learned things. I've changed my opinions on things. There are
at least things that I probably re- that I'd word differently. Sure. Or explain more, or
whatever, that I would change. Right. The editing, the editing could just never stop.
That's always the problem of being in the way we had. Especially after years, right?
Like go back to it. You're like, oh yeah, no. You know, that was pretty, really, more like
this yeah right.
But this kind of upset him because he's like, well, wait, should I read it or not?
Right? Like, you're telling me...
Right? Like, it's right.
And I had to say, like, at any time I talked to you, I'm doing my best.
Sure.
Right? I'm giving you my best case, my best understanding in that moment.
Right? But I hope that a few years from now, my understanding of these things will be better.
which reads I'll think that my understanding to
was to some degree wrong.
Right.
Unbelievable.
But I am very aware of my own subjectivity and fallibility.
And yeah, and so I'm sorry if that bothers people.
This researcher wanted me to present it as if, no,
I stand by every word of this.
And I'm like, hey, if I read it, I probably don't.
Like, that's not every word.
There.
Yeah.
And that's okay.
It's all right.
The world we live in, if human communications, right?
That's why most of what's on our bookshelves
is apocrypha.
Yes, yes.
Extrabiblical literature is everything except the Bible.
Yes.
Good digression, good digression.
Yeah.
Well, no, it is important to just ambiguous that though,
right?
It really is.
Yes, yes.
There is not, when St. Paul talks about the indwelling
of the Holy Spirit,
Hmm, right.
Read his epistles.
Show me where he talks about it as the Holy Spirit feeding us information.
Right.
About people, about the future, about their future, any of that.
The comparison he's always making is to the presence of God in the temple in the tabernacle.
And the Holy Spirit is the presence of God in us.
That's the comparison he makes over and over again.
And the presence of God in the tabernacle of the temple was not like whispering prophecies
to the priests while they served.
It wasn't a regular.
That wasn't a thing, right?
So I know that a lot of groups in America today, they think that's what the Holy Spirit does,
but that's frankly, that's not the Bible, man.
And especially if you're one of our Protestant friends, it being not in the Bible should
be super important to you.
I mean he's gonna give you utterance.
It's just gonna occur to you.
It's gonna like, you know,
the words are just gonna appear in your brain.
And, you know, yeah, or not.
Well, we won't go down that rabbit drill anymore.
Another, we already have, I think back to our,
we have prophecy, our episode of Prophets and Prophecy.
So, what else, what else are angels doing?
So angels are kind of, they're hanging out
in the world of thoughts.
What else?
Well, they're not hanging out, they have jobs.
Okay, you know what I mean?
That is where they are.
no angelic unemployment after the ascension.
No loafers.
But so the kind of thoughts, what are the kind of thoughts?
Right? Well, positive. Right? We don't just be positive like
wholesome or think good thoughts.
Pretty or nice. Right? That's what we're talking about. We're talking about
reminders and guidance, right? They're guiding us to God. So reminders of sin and repentance.
Right? Reminders of God's forgiveness of us. And the forgiveness that's available to us
We'll do a repent.
Reminders of God himself, right?
Reminders that the good things we have come from him, right?
Reminders, these are the kind of thoughts
we're talking about.
That would be the ones that angels are throwing our way,
as opposed to the ones that demons are throwing our way.
Yeah.
But we also want to, because we talked about how
Humans write bridge.
these two sort of layers of created reality,
the sort of angelic or noetic or the world of thoughts
and the physical and material world, again,
as we've said since literally the very beginning
of the show since the first episode,
these are not two different realities.
Yeah, these are not.
Natural supernatural.
That's not a North-O-Dex Christian.
Yeah.
No, there's not some barrier between the two.
You don't like, Astrali project to get into the other one.
Sorry, Dr. Strange.
And Professor, sorry, a lot of Astrali projection in Marvel comics.
I'm just realizing that.
I know, right.
Sorry, Dr. Strange.
Well, he is the Sorcerer Supreme, which I assume means he has all the toppings.
But anyway.
um
So, these aren't two different realities.
This is one created world, one creation of God that has these different elements and aspects
to it, that we can distinguish between.
And so, angels aren't restricted to this world of thoughts.
We see this in Scripture obviously.
associated with places and with things.
right? They're the angels who govern Philo quote, which we won't read again, right? The
sun, moon, and stars, right? And different parts of material creation, the nations as we
mentioned, right? And so there's not this barrier sort of between them, like, oh, though they're
just restricted to this thought world, they can't like sort of appear in the physical or
material world they can't ah
within the physical material world, they're not related in any way to it. No, they are. Right?
That's yeah. But they don't live in both the way we do because they don't have material bodies
like us. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Right. They live in one, but it's not separated from the other
part, the other. They function as spirits as spirits. Yes. That's their main function is a sort of
influencing, you know, thing.
That's what we're saying.
There we go.
So make sure you like and subscribe.
Yeah.
Click the little notification button.
Click the bell.
You know, every time a new thought appears.
Exactly.
All right.
Well, that's the second half of this episode of Lord of Spirits.
Talk about angels.
We'll be right back with the third and final half.
See you soon.
People often complain that the divine litter...
is always the same, weak after weak.
But every ritual, phrase, and action in the service
has meaning and purpose.
Drawing in worshipers with its hymns and prayers
and allowing ordinary people to leave the world
and enter heaven for a short time.
In the new book, Blessed Is the Kingdom,
Father Stavros, Akrotarian Akis, a long time parish priest,
offers reflections on the text of the divine liturgy
of Saint John Christophe.
to help readers learn to pray the liturgy and to understand and appreciate the mystery that unfolds each time it is celebrated.
Available now at store.enginefaith.com
Again, that is store.enginefaith.com
And we're back. It's the third half of this episode of the Lord of Scruits Podcasts once again, we're pre-recorded.
so we're not taking any calls.
We don't know what'll happen if you call.
that number, but we're not taking any calls.
But most of you, exactly.
Most of you don't live anyways.
So, yeah, so, you know, it's the same experience as always.
Anyway, we're talking about angels
and we just finished up our second half
where we're talking about the sort of the nitty gritty
of angelic activity in the world.
So what else is there?
I mean, we, we, we,
Yeah.
There's more to say about their ministry,
but there's some interesting things about what angels
have to do with humans exactly.
I think that we could talk about here.
Yes, yeah, yeah.
So we talked about it the first half.
We talked about sort of how God administers creation
through angels.
And then a second half, we talked a little bit about how angels
interact with us within the created world.
Yeah.
And now this third half, not to show our hands too much, but you might detect some madness
to our method.
We're going to talk about how Angelic beings function in terms of our relationship upwards
toward God.
And so one window we get into that is the reference that Christ makes to
guardian angels. Yeah. When he talks about the little ones who we are not to offend because
their angels are always before the throne of the Father in heaven, right? They're angels,
right? So they have angels, hence the reference to guardian angels, but it's not just that,
Oh, they have a guardian angel and he's going to come smite you, right?
If you.
If you offend them, but that angel is always right is standing before the father of heaven. So what's it? What's it doing?
Yeah, is it supposed to be guarding them? Why is it hanging out?
Yeah, well, what are you doing there?
The space doesn't work the same in the west realm as it does. Yeah.
Yeah, so if the if in the first half we were coming at it sort of top down, right?
God, tour creation. Now we're sort of coming at it sort of bottom up.
right? And in that sense we see this angel clearly that Christ is talking about.
These angels are functioning as sort of intermediaries, right? They're
interceding with, speaking to praying to God, communicating to God about what is
going on with their charges, these little ones on earth who are being abused
to some way, right? And Christ is saying...
you should be aware of that before you mistreat.
One of these that, right?
This is what you're doing is being reported to God.
Now, again,
does that mean God wouldn't know otherwise?
Right?
Why does it Christ just say,
hey, God sees what you do
and he sees how you treat people?
He knows when you're sleeping,
he knows when you're awake.
I mean, he does.
That would be a true statement, right?
Yes, right.
We're not saying God doesn't, right?
Like, that would be a true statement, right?
But this points to a reality that again, right, out of love, God has given these angelic
beings this intermediary role, right, that they are participants in and share in this
relationship of love between God and this human person he's created.
So hard to imagine being bioguardian angel would be any kind of privilege as opposed to
being someone else's maybe not, but in this sense it is.
In this sense it is.
This by the way, right?
We talked about every mention this. We mentioned this.
in terms of the quote we've mentioned several times from St. Andrew of Crete,
but the idea of the devil falling through envy.
This of course is understood to be talking about envy of the sort of special relationship
between God and humanity.
That isn't shared in the same sense
by God and angels. See Hebrews
right because of the incarnation.
about which of the angels did God ever say, right?
And he responded to that with envy, right?
Yeah.
But the correct response, right,
and what we see with the angels who did fall out of envy
or anything else, right, is that they were given a role
within that relationship.
That relationship between humans and God is sh-
shared with the angelic beings.
There are participants in that.
Right? And we see the participating in that.
The angels and the stars, well, the same thing.
But who were singing in Luke 2 when Christ is born?
Right? It's not that they're this third thing
Cut out of
You know like God you know they were the first draft and then humans and God likes humans better
Right like someone's family. I don't know who's I could be talking about where you know
The mom just loves the second child more right. I mean just
It's a thing you know that happened sometimes
Right, but that's not what we're talking about with God. Yes, right right
God loves angels, the angels he created just as much as he would see created.
Right? That's not, it's not like, right?
But again, different roles, different purposes, right?
But angels are part of that community.
They're not cut out from it.
They're not separated from it unless they separate themselves from it.
Right?
So the devil falls through every meaning the devil wasn't happy with.
that role that he was given by God.
And this is the story of rebellion sort of all through the scriptures.
Right.
And the story of sin as rebellion as a whole is God gives us a role to play.
He makes us who we are and places us where he places us in history,
in time, in space, and the family we're born into. Right.
Gives us yeah
different gifts, right? Different places, different times, different, all right. All
these things are different and all these things are kind of given to us without
our say so. And the core of sinful rebellion is being unhappy with that and
wanting something else.
Wanting to be someone or something we're not wanting to have some gift from
God that.
He hasn't given us, not wanting the ones he has given us, not wanting to be where he has put us,
wanting to be somewhere else. That's the core of rebellion. But so angels are a part of that.
And having this intermediary function is how they're part of that love and part of that relationship.
Yeah. So again, they're not necessary there. Yes, God does.
He doesn't need an angel to tell him.
Right.
To report to him. Right? Yep.
Nonetheless,
reach a Bible, reach a Job.
Okay, very clear, angels come and report things going on on earth to God.
All the way to Revelation.
Right?
Ah, that's there. We see angels bringing the prayers of the saints to God in Revelation, post-Decension.
Yeah.
Yeah. Right. Do they need to? Does God not know about the prayers of the saints unless they get brought to a bit of
bowl by an angel? Of course he does. Yeah. But the angels are given this role. Right. And it's very clear. I mean, abundantly clear, it's that can
a couple Jewish literature, right, that angels have this intercess-
a role. Right. And it's a double-it-stripe, including like the book of Revelation. These
purposes, though it is canonical, right? It is also technically part of second-temporal
literature. I mean, maybe technically not because the temple was destroyed 25 years before
it was written. Sorry, Predorus. But you know what I mean. Now, within pre-Christian Judaism
Yeah.
ongoing in Christianity. Right, it's important that this idea that there are these intermediaries
involved with prayer, with intercession, right, with speaking to God on behalf of people of
the world and what's going on in the world. This is in addition to not in place of the other,
right? So it's not that the angels prayed for people so they didn't have to.
Yeah, yeah, or like they don't get in the
way. That's a frequent criticism from some Protestants is like angels, you know, get
it. If you talk to an angel, it gets in the way between you and God as though there is,
that's even a possibility. Right. And this is at the problem with asking the question,
right? Well, wait, right. So I pray, God, here's my prayer. God knows I pray, right?
Bye.
Why does some angel or some glorified saint have to come and offer my prayer to God?
Right or double down on it or pray with me. Again, there's no have to.
There's no have to. Yeah. And if you're going to ask that question, you might as well ask,
well why pray at all? God already knows what I'm thinking and feeling.
Why do I have to vocalize it?
Why should I confess my sins to God or anybody else?
God knows what I did.
He knows about sins I did notice and forgot about.
Or don't realize his, or say God knows,
God already knows.
So why bother?
Yeah, I mean, the same argument can be used against,
against prayer entirely, you know, like,
why are you saying?
Why pray at all?
Between you and God.
Why confess it at all?
Right?
Yeah.
Even confessing it directly to God.
Why he already knows?
Yeah.
Right? Yep.
That'd make a whole lot of sense, right?
But this idea, you know, I was having a discussion with, with uh, or the Jewish person and
they were trying to minimize because really honestly even in post-Christian Jewish tradition,
there's an intercession of
angels and saints, but he was trying to sort of minimize that part of the tradition and said to me,
give me one example. He said, can you give me one example of second temple literature of
Saint George was a receding for people. And I said, man, I can't think of a single second temple
Jewish interpreter or even later Jewish interpreter for that matter who understands Rachel weeping
for her children when Israel went into exile.
would judo it at exile as anything other than Rachel weeping for her
children. Yes, not some weird who did take it literally. They
also got literally that the spirit of Rachel, right? It was
saying was weeping seeing her right before God crying out to
God over what was happening, right? And then St Matthew of course
supplies that to the slot of the innocence.
Yeah, and I would therefore see no reason why anyone would understand St. Matthew to be interpreting you that any less literally
Then all the other Jewish interpreters living at the time he did
Right
So
Yeah, this is this is just a thing
Right
Not because it's quote unquote necessary
But now when we talk about this, when we talk about angels or glorified saints
interceding, the most common thing, the most common thing, that people who oppose
that idea or practice or just get the EBGB from it, right, the most common
Verse that you hear in response.
It's first Timothy 2 verse.
verse 5. We're now going to tell you why you need to stop that. Yeah. Okay. First
Timothy 2 verse 5, which is depending on your translation roughly for there is one
mediator between God and man, the man Christ Jesus. Yes. I can start out. See? There's
one mediator. Nobody else. You don't need any of these people praying for you. That's
never applied by the way to asking people in the...
church to pray for you. Hey, there's one meter between God and man, you guys. Yeah, why are you
asking me to pray for you? Why do you pray directly to God? Right? You never hear that. But yeah,
that's the verse you hear. Okay. So there should be a tip off to you. Because that word for
in the translation at the beginning basically means because.
So if you have a sentence here, the begins with beca-
It's not even a really a sense. It's a clause within a sentence. It's part of a sentence, right?
So there's something something something something
right in first Timothy two one through four something something something because
There is one media between God and man to man Christ Jesus and the way it's quoted you would think that the something something something something
The first four verses is you don't need anyone to it or seed for you
right?
But lo and behold!
When you go to 1 Timothy 2, verse 1, context.
Yes, 1 Timothy 2, verse 1, to see the beginning of the sentence.
The beginning of the sentence is, say Paul, say,
I desire that intercessions be made for all men.
Wait, that can't be right.
Yes, and he adduberates your kings, rulers, princes, you should pray for everyone.
Pray for everyone, intercede for everyone.
before God, because there is one mediator between God and man, the man Christ Jesus. So folks who
quote that against the idea of intercession are abusing scripture. You are abusing St. Paul.
You are quoting St. Paul out of context. You're quoting the Bible, the scriptures out of context
to say the exact opposite of what they are saying. That's why you need to stop it.
Yeah, let's be...
because there's one mediator that you should do this interest.
Yes.
Because you are literally trying to make the opposite point
by quoting the Bible out of context.
Yeah, obviously the mediation that Jesus is doing is not.
Is it different kind of mediation than intercessory prayer?
Because mediation, the word mediation,
it just means being in the middle between, you know,
but it shouldn't be taken in an utterly literal way.
Right.
Well, I think it is in a literal,
literal might not be the right word.
there. Yeah, yeah. But like, you know, like you shouldn't take the you shouldn't take the image and
push it to every possibility. So like if I if I pray for you, I'm being a mediator, but that doesn't
and that sense I'm between you and God, but not in the sense of like, don't get me between me and
me and God. Yeah. No, like I'm not cutting off access. Just right. Jesus is not cutting off.
Did it addition not in place of? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Like just yes, just like Christ,
Does it cut off your access to the father?
Right.
Quite the opposite.
But so no, what St. Paul is talking about there with the mediation and then how that
because works in the sentence.
Okay.
Any of those people who want to quote it the other way explained to me how the because works
in that sentence.
Okay.
Because I can explain how that because works in that sentence.
If that St. Paul is talking about the incarnation.
media it's between God.
in man in his person. Yeah, he's he's both right. And that's why it says there's one
meteor between God and man, the man Christ Jesus. Right. This is and so Saint Paul has received
this tradition of angelic intercession. He's a Jewish person in the first century AD. They
believe in this. Okay? And he's saying because
of who Christ is because of the incarnation and the ascension. Now human prayers and human
intersections are as powerful, if not more powerful, than angelic intersections. That's
the argument here, that's the because, right? Because of the incarnation and the
and humanity be exceeded at the right hand of God.
That's why Saint Paul wants humans to pray and intercede
for the whole world, for everyone in it,
for all kinds of people.
And the incarnation lies behind, as we were saying earlier,
call in Bargdermann.
Um, the incarnation lies behind so much of St. Paul's.
theology. Just referring to Christians now as holy ones. Remember, holy ones that gets translated
saints in the New Testament and often not in the Old Testament, holy ones is what's used
to refer to angels in the Old Testament.
Yeah.
Angels.
And he refers to humans in the Church of By that title, right? So this is a connection between
humans and angels that's being made. And here that's being applied to intercessions. And
the reason there's a parallel.
there between humans and angels is because of the incarnation of Christ. Through which
humanity has been exalted, even above angels such that Saint Paul also said, and we talked
about earlier, we're going to judge them one day. So again, this intercession is not only
is it not in place of, right? It's in addition to, right? I ask someone to pray for me while
I also pray, right, add these
someone I asked to pray for me can be anyone who's alive, which includes the saints, right?
Yes.
And angels.
That's, isn't necessary.
Okay, we're not saying necessary.
Here's that efficiency thing.
Rhearing its ugly head again.
I've used that rearing its ugly head.
Rhearing its horrid head again.
Gotta bury it up a little.
Um, right?
That that and and no one is saying that, right?
We all understand this.
We all understand that like, you don't convince God by reaching a certain number of people
praying for something.
Yes.
Right.
Like we had one, two few Facebook likes.
So the kid died, right?
We know that doesn't happen, right?
God's not like counting.
Okay.
Well, we've got 87 people praying for this now.
If it hits 100 I guess I'll do it.
Right? Like that's not how this works. Right?
None of us thinks that you're going to like convince God by getting someone important or influential or a particular saint to pray for you.
Okay. Like, well, if I could just get, you know,
the patron orric of Constantinople to pray for this for me or celebrity pastor or whomever, right?
I think has God's favor this week or St.
Oxenius to, right?
If I could just get them to pray for this, then God will do it.
Right? We don't think that.
Right? No, none of us think that.
Right? Hopefully.
It's an expression of love for one another.
It's an expression of love. It's a communion with each other.
Alright, my pressure
pray for each other, right? Not because they think that, oh well, you know, if they just pray
themselves, God won't do it. But if we all pray, then God will. We don't think that, right?
But that coming together and praying for each other and praying for the same things together
is an expression of our love for each other. Yeah. In fact, praying for someone really sincerely
praying for someone.
With some effort.
is one of the highest forms of love for that person.
There's been this demeaning lately of thoughts and prayers
and demean thoughts all you want.
Like, you were always on my mind,
you know, nice Willie Nelson song, but who cares, right?
Just thinking, that makes you cry
at the animal shelter commercial.
But anyway.
Right, so no prayers to have values for the highest forms of love, but it is also true.
Some of the pushback against that thoughts and prayers thing does have a correct point
in that that doesn't replace other forms of love.
Right?
Oh, this person needs help.
This person needs a ride to the emergency room.
I'm going to pray for him.
I'm going to pray for him real hard tonight that someone helps them.
Right?
No, obviously.
You also help the person.
Right
Again, there's no reason to separate those two things.
Oh, I don't just pray about things.
I actually go and do them and help people
and make them happen or on the other side, you know.
Well, I pray for people and that's the most important.
No, you do both.
Poor kid, all those dose.
But actual intercessory prayer for someone
is a beautiful expression of
of your love for them.
And we'll change how you've viewed them
and we'll change your relationship with them.
Yeah, I, I, I,
Well, they'll certainly get God to do what you want.
Yeah, I mean, God's.
I thought what prayer is anyway.
Right.
Yeah, I mean, one of the things that I tell people a lot
is, is especially if they're having a relationship problem
with somebody, which I mean, that's a lot of what
confession is about, right?
Is, you know, are you earnestly, consistently praying
for that person?
because if you're not, then you're like...
Cutting your legs out from underneath yourself.
You know, it's not gonna get better probably.
Yep.
Yeah.
So,
in summary of the last two episodes, what has all this been about? Where has all this been going?
Kind of nowhere, but I'm gonna try and put a bow on it anyway.
What's all this?
What's all this then?
And that's
If we take all these things we've been talking about in the last two episodes, I think about
what does it mean for angels and demons to fight?
Yeah, we actually got a question in the Facebook group.
I think it just came in through this morning actually.
Someone was saying that they had heard this idea that when natural disasters happen,
you know, that earthquakes or big storms or hurricanes, whatever, that that's war in
the heavenly realms.
you know, tight.
I thought Thunder was Angel's bowling, but we should have a we should have an episode titled Angel's bowling. That's an idea. There we go.
So, uh, yeah. So, uh, sorry, Frank Peretti fans. Uh, he had the sort of highlander version of, uh,
Oh.
of Angel Demon fights, right?
Lots of big heavy sword swinging
and trying to to capitate each other
because there could be only one.
Which is cool, I mean.
Cool, yeah.
You know.
But who wants to live forever?
Fun, fun read, but yeah.
And Harry your Cavalry, you can't do everything, man.
But again, not what we're talking about.
All right.
What we're talking about, honestly, is what we've been talking about with the world of thoughts.
Right? The battle is really the battle for the mind.
Right? The battle is about what thoughts am I going to nurture and turn into ideas and what kind of ideas am I going to do?
Let's go.
come up with and how am I going to try and implement them and use them in the world?
And what am I going to bring about?
What direction am I going to go?
Because the whole game for the demonic, whether we're talking about the devil himself or
demons or whatever kind of demons or whatever that we talked about last episode, the whole
end game for them is to destroy as much of humanity as they possibly can.
as we talked about early on when we were talking about the fall of
safe.
in our very early episodes, right, the fall of the devil.
This whole Miltonian thing of,
oh, he's gonna overthrow God and make himself God.
And I'm like, oh, okay, what's step one to do that?
Yeah.
You can't do that.
That's not a thing.
This is not paganism.
There's not a way to do that.
Right?
It's not like God has God powers that you can seize
with a cosmic siphon or something.
That's Galactus and Dr. Doom.
Right, totally different thing, right?
That's not how any of this works, right? You can't do that. The devil can't do that, right?
The devil fell out of envy, envy of humanity. He can destroy, try and destroy humanity. He can try
destroy humans. Who God loves. That's his shot, right? And a great part of the story of Scripture
is that the links that God goes to to redeem and save you
humanity from that fate. So the battlefield between angels and demons is your
mind, your heart, your thoughts. That's where spiritual warfare is happening. It's
in terms of sin. It's in terms of your enslavement or your freedom.
Regarding sin. It's in terms of how much you will yield to the demons or how
much you will align your will.
and your work in the world with God, right?
All of these things we've been talking about,
this is what spiritual warfare is.
This is where angels and demons are fighting.
This is where you have to pick which side you're going
to follow, right?
And the stakes are whether you live eternally
or you perish.
That's honestly it.
And so in that regard,
you know, talking about demons the last episode,
the name angels in this episode, it's like
Deuteronomy, right?
Here is life and death, blessings and nurses, right?
Each of us has a choice to make not just once,
but over and over again through our lives as to which,
which one of those directions we're gonna go
and which of those we're gonna receive?
And those are pretty much my final thoughts.
Oh.
See what I did there?
That's great.
I will add just a
little bit. Yeah, I think, you know, in one of the things that's that's set a lot these days,
and I think it's true. I mean, based on my personal experiences with people is that there is a
growing sense of isolation and loneliness. And I'm not going to, you know, draw like a straight
dotted line from that back to this kind of flattening of the spiritual world.
that happens with the Reformation where all the angels and saints are kind of pushed off to the side and it's just got up there and then us directly underneath them.
But I do think that that theological outlook isn't helping and maybe is the context for some of this sense of isolation.
You know, we've said since 2020 on this show that it's a crowded spiritual world.
It's crowded out there.
There's this whole...
Well...
as scripture says, great cloud of witnesses, right?
The angels, the saints who are present with us all the time.
This is why someone like Sinan the Great
or the other hermits and anchorites and ascetics,
they go off to be alone.
And indeed, the Greek word for them, Monachos,
monk, it refers to being alone,
but they actually have a very strong sense of not being alone.
So they're alone as far as the world is concerned,
but they're not really...
alone because they are engaging with the spiritual world, the noetic world, to use the technical term.
And so I believe very much that one of the things that can help us in this time of isolation and
loneliness is to renew our sense, or maybe for many of us, begin having a sense of this crowded
spiritual world to engage with the angels in the saints.
by asking for their prayers, by asking for their help. And again, it's not instead of God.
It's in addition to your prayers to God. As Orthodox Christians, if you were to add up all of the
prayers that we say in terms of our private prayer, our liturgical prayers, whatever,
the vast majority of them are directed directly towards God Himself, Father, Son, and Holy
spirit. And then we also have
prayers to the saints, to the angels, right? Just like for most Christians, the vast majority
of your prayer is to God directly, and you also ask for your friends to pray for you. When
you ask for something, by the way, that is literally what prayer is. I mean, that's just what
the English word prayer means in its most basic sense. And so it's for our spiritual health,
and in many cases for our mental health.
connecting with this larger community, the community in Christ, that is both the
scene and the unseen at the same time. I think it's just absolutely so so vital
for us. So that wraps up this episode of the Lord of Spears podcast. Thank you
very much for listening everybody. This was not a live episode. We did we
pre-recorded it. So we didn't take any calls but we'd like to hear from you. You
can email us at LordofSpearsNaturedFate.com. You can message us at our Facebook
page you can leave us a
email at speakpipe.com slash Lord of Spirits. And if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity,
or you need help in finding a parish, because that's critical, head over to Orthodoxintro.org.
And join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern, 4 p.m. Pacific.
It's fine, it's cool. You can say that we're nothing, but you know the truth.
If you're on Facebook, you can follow our page, you can join our discussion group, super active.
leave reviews
and ratings everywhere, and share this show with a friend or family member.
Finally, be sure to go to www.hfade.com.strokesupport.com and help make sure we and lots of
other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
I guess I'm the fool with our arms out like an angel through the car's sunroof.
Thank you, good night, and God bless you all.
You've been listening to The Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Steven Daymak and Father Steven DeYoung.
a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels
round about the throne, and the beasts, and the elders,
and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000,
and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land
that was slain to receive power, and riches,
and wisdom, and strength, and honor, and glory, and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.